One of the project documents that we talked about in the last lecture was a business case.
Well it's really important to have a good understanding of the business case because that can affect
your entire project can affect where the project even is launched.
So let's look at the characteristics of a business case and how it affects a project.
First off of project business case is really an economic feasibility study.
It's can we afford to do the project.
Is it financially feasible.
Does it make sense to invest in this project.
So what's the validity of the project is it really going to create something that we can use and that's
going to bring US business value.
It helps to make future project management decisions and actions based on the finances in the business
value that the project is going to create or that's a risk score that may not be of value.
We're going to stay away from that.
The business case is maintained throughout the project.
So as there are new discoveries there are new additions there are some changes.
Then you have to update the business case to show whether it's justified in need it or characteristics
about the business case the project sponsor is accountable for the development in the maintenance of
the business case not the project manager the project sponsor maintains the business case.
Now the PM is responsible for making recommendations and by saying this is why we need this change or
this supports our business value supports the vision or strategy or what.
What's already been laid out in the business case.
But it's the sponsor that maintains it and the business case could also be at a program level a program.
You have lots of individual projects but the program oversees those individual projects.
Let's talk about the business case and business needs before a project is launched.
We can go into the business case or create a business case as to why do we need the project.
So what's prompting the need for action.
A business case defines the business problem or the opportunity that the price of the project is going
to solve or get.
So what's the problem.
How are we solving it.
Or is there an opportunity that's going to have some definite business value that we should go out and
grab it and get it like a market window or there's some opportunity or the customer request us to do
the project.
And so that's good business value.
It identifies the stakeholders that are affected their business stakeholders or people or groups that
are affected by the project and they can also affect the project.
So we try to identify the stakeholders as early as possible.
The business case often will identify the scope of the project so it doesn't have to create a total
project scope statement.
But generally it's a high level scope of what are we talking about here.
So if we were to do a business case for new software that we were going to create or the business case
to replace all of our laptops in our organization or a business case to create and build a warehouse
it would be pretty able to describe the scope of what we're doing.
We're building software replacing laptops or we're building a warehouse.
So the business case would describe that project in some level of detail a business case is also used
in Project determination should we do the project or not.
So a business case will look at the scope of the project the value it brings.
Then how does it fit with the organization strategies its goals and objectives.
If it doesn't support the strategies goals and objectives we probably don't need to be doing the project
what about root cause for solving a problem.
What are the root cause root cause is just that what's the problem and what's causing it.
And then we can have a project to go and attack that root cause.
What about an opportunity.
So I talked about there's an opportunity that we're going to have business value.
So where's the opportunity the market or a customer request is an opportunity.
What about a gap analysis.
So we want to do some construction with a new type of material but we don't really have the skills to
do that type of material.
So we have a gap analysis as part of our our project determination part of our business case.
What are the known risks.
So if you're doing a project in health care there all sorts of known risk in your application area or
in I.T. or in construction that just by being in that discipline you have some insight into what risks
are there.
What are the critical success factors.
How do you know you're successful.
What would constitute success in this project.
So really important to have that up front to have a vision into if these things are true that I know
my project is successful.
So the business case helps paint that picture gives us goals to work towards as the project manager.
The last one here is some decision criteria that the business case can make a recommendation on.
We should do this or should not do this as an organization.
So some decision criteria a business case can also do an analysis of a situation.
So what I'm talking about here is should we do it or should we not based on this opportunity based on
this problem based on you know a customer request.
So should we do it or should we not.
So we're going to look at three elements recommendations that we make.
We have required desired an optional required would be you must do it.
You must do it.
So I'm talking about here is we're creating a piece of software and the requirement is it has to be
secure the data has to be secure so you must do it in order for the project to be successful.
That's one of the criteria is that the data must be secure.
Desired is.
Well we would like this to come true but if it's not it's OK.
So an example here of desired would be we would like for you to also make a mobile app that fits with
the desktop app.
But if you can't get to it now we can do it later or some flavor of that.
So we want it to be desired.
So it's it's a good idea but it's not or it's not a deal breaker for us.
And the third one is just optionals not necessarily it's not essential.
And that may be the ability to print from the mobile app.
So not really something we're worried about.
So required desired and optional then we get into the recommendation for a project.
This is me in the future.
I have a good feeling.
I don't know a whole lot.
Anyway let's talk about a recommendation for a project.
So out of the business case we could say don't do the project do nothing just keep business as usual.
Do the minimum work possible.
Don't invest too much.
Just do what the minimum to seize the opportunity the bare minimum or do the most you could do do more
than the minimum work possible.
So seize the opportunity and really go after it with gusto.
So these are three typical recommendations often from a business analysts and they all sound kind of
negative don't they do nothing to the minimum or just do more than the minimum work possible in your
project.
All right so that's the characteristics of a business case.
Good job.